what is it how do you see a work getting
gave me I had it like in my head cuz I
just read it before oh no no no if
you've got if you've got a thing all
lined up go ahead I just I did like five
minutes of research is looking at the
etymology of about the origins of the
word where that was that was all no I
just think you just say for for the
beginning part but the question was and
then we take the turns and I what is
Redemption and how do you see a working
in game B's you know it's there if I
don't hold on to it so strongly right
would anyone like to go first
I think Eric wants to go first so yeah
etiology of it which I just looked up
today is it's to do with paying again
yeah that's what what's what redemption
means so there the Damier is to do with
payment Andrey's obviously to repay and
so I mean there is that sense in
everyday English right he redeem of out
show you spent when you spend your vow
to you redeem it so there is there is
that part of it but it has also come to
mean like forgiveness from sin kind of
thing and I mean I think that's probably
the sense in which the question was
asked to go with more in that kind of
sense the question was asked but
nevertheless the roots like the roots of
the word lie in the notion of paying
back paying again and so my biggest
question around this notion of
redemption has always been kind of along
the lines of his Redemption something
that is an inner process right you know
you've done wrong and so you do what is
necessary both internally and in terms
of you know making reparations or making
things right with the people that you've
wronged is that redemption or redemption
something that is granted by the outside
world to you and and that's always been
the main question I've had centered
around this but it seems as though from
the root of the word that is that it's
that it's about you right it's about you
paying back for what you have done kind
of thing that that's that's the root of
the word is in is in repayment so that's
that I mean I'm not saying it's right
but just because of the etiology of the
word that's the lie
I'm gonna take on it and if you do see
it as an inner process of putting right
what's gone wrong kind of thing it
doesn't have to be a grievous sin right
it doesn't have to be raping a baby kind
of thing you know that this is a
constant process of it's just the worst
thing that pops into our head but you
know if you see redemption as a sort of
constant process of improvement right so
noticing where you have fallen short of
you ideals that you hold for yourself
and you know doing the work necessary to
fall less short of those the next time
around kind of thing and so I see it you
know like so many things in the last six
months or so start to see these things
as directionality is right a little bit
more of that a little bit less of that
gets you going in the right direction
and so I I kind of see it like that so
I'll stop there I think that's okay I
wanted to say all right did you wanna
connect security I too looked up you
know the words and there being two you
know there being two different one you
know two different definitions and you
know you know the first one being the
action of saving or being saved from sin
you know that it's something that's
external like like your that your
redemption comes from the external and
then the other one is Eric exactly what
you were talking about in terms of the
the debt and one of the things that my
husband and I talk a lot about is the
way that debt language plays a role in
relationships and in turn in and how so
much of what is happening in our culture
right now is everything is transactional
and it's a debt and so when if we're
talking about how does redemption you
know I don't remember the exact wording
of the second part of the question in
terms of how does redemption work in
game B but to me you know there is
there's too
there's two pieces because there is the
the part of that's my internal you know
I have committed a I have sinned I have
missed them you know the definition of
I've missed the mark or my mark and and
I'm trying to figure out how to redeem
you know how to pay that debt to myself
but there is also the debt with other
people you know that there is redemption
a process of redemption with other
people in game a it there is a process
of redemption for certain crimes we have
the process of if you if you've
committed certain types of crimes you go
to prison and when you have when you
have completed your sentence that you
know that's your path to redemption and
in some cases that you know if you if
you've taken a life you know there
there's maybe that maybe that is an
appropriate way of a path to redemption
there's a there's a story that I've
heard recently about a tribe in Africa
if you know someone if someone kills
someone else the family has a choice
they can either drown the person who
killed the their family member or they
can forgive them and the question is is
do you want justice or do you want like
the emotional salvation that comes from
for forgiveness and people get to make
that decision and so you know I think I
am I do a lot of work in 12-step in the
12-step world and I talk about that a
lot and in 12-step there is the process
of amends that you you know you do them
you take a personal moral inventory it's
your
figuring out how have I missed the mark
based on my standards for myself and in
what ways have I harmed others in that
process and how do I need to make amends
and sometimes the men's is to myself and
sometimes it's a financial amends
sometimes it's you know something more
significant and I think that I think the
12-step model of the amends process is
an interesting part of that and talking
about it in terms of the morality
it being an individual person's morality
but in order to get to the place in game
B where it's where other in-game a
everybody's trying to hold everyone else
to their moral standards and how do you
how do you live in a world where it's
one person's moral standard is not the
same as another and one person's path
one's person's choice of path to
redemption is different than someone
else's and I think those are complicated
confusing nuanced conversations that are
important and right now it's in game a
it's if you said something that was
colorful and no it's politically correct
ten years ago you get canceled and
because there is it there is no path to
redemption yet and it's up to us to hold
you to our moral standards and I just
agree with that wholeheartedly and but
how do we how do we get
servile with being with everyone having
their own set of morality and how do we
live together in an environment that
does that I'm not sure okay I'm done
hey Kyra Oh funny because I asked the
redemption question I was very much
thinking about it in a group format not
how do you come to individual redemption
but how is a group do we decide when
somebody's no longer part of the group
and is there a path back to that because
it's come up in several conversations
that kicking someone out is at least
historically death you can't find
another group that's no longer the case
even inking hey you know what I mean if
your immediate family disowns you you
can find a new family it's possible if
and so there's also a piece of like does
your reputation follow you do you get to
start over afresh and start with a new
group and you know in some cases I would
say yeah and in other cases no because
you need people need to know what
happened before and who makes those
decisions who gets to decide what
follows you and what doesn't follow you
and that there is the group itself gets
to kind of decide when and how people
are kicked out in the path to redemption
but I think there's a higher level group
that needs to kind of make sure there's
a place for everyone or at least own
that kicking someone out of all over the
places equals death and that is canceled
culture it's like not only am I not
talking to you nobody can talk to you
and I'm not talking to anyone who talks
to you and like this bridge is burnt
like it's done and so but like we don't
we do that with a sense of like oh but
that doesn't mean death I just want you
to let go live on is a hermit somewhere
it's like that's death is humanity like
that is actually making sure that there
is a place for every individual even if
that place isn't within our group and
there's a level we have to deal with
that with well well owning that truth
and if it's kicked out of the higher
level then that does mean death and so
at the at the smaller group level you
can have
right you don't belong here for whatever
metric reason maybe you didn't do
anything egregious but like you're not
intellectually capable or you're not
emotionally capable or you're not
there's some metric that like no sorry
there's a barrier to entry and you don't
make it but there's somewhere for you
yeah and there's a difference between a
group that is like you're you luck into
entering like your family right where
it's like getting kicked out of your
family should be a higher barrier but it
exists and some some people it's not a
high barrier it's like oh you happen to
be born gay you know you're not part of
our family anymore but the fact that the
groups that we choose to be part of are
and is there a difference right between
like getting kicked out of your family
versus getting kicked out of a hobby
Girt that you're part of right and and
what that is and I think that there is a
big piece of that word justice and
whatever the opposite of justice is like
we want that justice at the same time it
stops the other piece it stops the light
right but you want them to get better do
you want to society that functions or do
we want to have justice do we want to
have revenge on people and those are
things that gain be whatever it is it's
gonna have to figure out because of all
of these levels and the individual and
the group and bigger meta groups of like
decided on these levels and to own that
if you kick somebody out of the meta
group level it equals death and to own
that so that you're literally giving
them the death penalty even if you were
not firing a bullet at them is it worth
it did they do something so egregious do
we agree with the death I'm holding it
right so that's that's fine Jubilee I
liked that part of understanding what
understanding the reaper cut you know
like okay if I'm choosing to kick
someone out of all you know of all
groups then I am you know essentially
causing them death and you know it when
groups lived in you know tribes of
Dunbar number you know there was a you
knew that you knew that if someone was
kicked out of the tribe then it was
death and whereas now like well you can
just go and you can just join another
tribe or you know but the the cancel
culture you know wanting to you know
it's this all-or-nothing you have you
know if you don't agree with us and and
act in the way that we want you to act
in every situation then you are
violating you know you you you have
violated our moral standards and
therefore deserve punishment and I've
been involved in a lot of discussions
recently about you know what it means to
have different moral frameworks and how
do you I think part of the path in game
B is loosening our grip on our moral
frameworks because you know and in the
game be Facebook group you know there's
the recent stuff that's happened of
people getting removed from the group
and you know making a decision whether
or not you know it's like making a
decision about this how destructive an
individual is to a group versus the okay
this is going to be disruptive for a
while
but but trusting that you're gonna come
out the other the other end with a sense
of what you know with a better sense of
with a better sense of reality and I
don't know like yeah it's it's uh it's a
confusing yeah absolutely any question
about the 12-step program which I'm so
much for you're within a matys
who decides on what the amends is is it
the person that was wronged or the
person going through the 12 steps the
person going through the 12 steps yeah
cuz that's me is like problematic and
yet I get like both ways it's
problematic right like you get to come
to me and I get to tell you what the
amends is but if you're truly making
amends listen I stole from you I lied to
you I did like what would make that
right is to me the amounts right and I
then get to choose whether I can do it
or not right if it's like well pay back
every cent you you did never lie to me
again I don't know if I can do that but
sure or tell me every lie you ever told
me it's like that seems like an immense
but for the person to get to choose what
the amends is but I guess it's cuz
you're getting right as opposed to
getting right with the relationships
it's more like you're right and it is
it's about you getting right with
yourself versus getting right with the
relationship now a lot of times when you
do it it's you've the most often you
know one of the parts of the 12 steps is
that you go through you go through them
with a sponsor someone who has been
through them before someone who helps
you you know it's like you're not just
simply making that decision and you're
making you know and you and you know
you're making a decision based on any
kind of what you can what you're capable
of and what you know and what fits the
crime and you know it's getting right
with your own conscience there's
something there for the path to
redemption game because it's like I mean
the sponsors not neutral they're not a
neutral party they're clearly more in it
for the person they know then the person
wronged but if this
in time they've been wronged by people
they've you know been that partying
right down to it I know that's not an OK
in amends you need to do more than that
but having that kind of external but
loving in a way support system to say
hey this is the path to redemption and I
can you can never actually make a
Redemption with that person like I
sponsor I don't get to choose whether
the other person forgives you and
whether that's that's okay but I can say
that I can help you do that where it's
not just you deciding well I told them
the truth they should forgive me I'm all
good and it's them deciding and give me
every possession you've ever had and
it's for the opposite maybe someone
comes up with a horrible Redemption and
there is this like I just say forgive me
and like to be able to hold that space
more well na de charlie and it's also
one of the big pieces of it is it's not
going in with the desert of course
you're you may have the desire to be
forgiven but you may go in and and maybe
all it is is that you know Ana is making
an amends for something that you said
you know the some way that you've you
know wronged someone by something that
you've said or you know gossip or you
know something like that and saying what
you have to say and then sitting there
quietly whatever comes back at you and
not getting defensive and just trusting
that whatever you know whatever comes
back in return is appropriate and you
know more often than not like you hear
stories in 12-step all the time where
somebody goes and makes an amends and
the person is still angry and doesn't
want to forgive them and then years
later they're going and doing their own
amends so like it is this looks
definitely a circular thing because you
know it's like somebody can hold on to
their whatever their anger is and they
you say that's not good enough
and ultimately it usually ends up
poisoning that person more than it does
the person who made way more than the
person who made the amends mm-hm
but then it also is like so you're there
to make the amends and you've left them
with poison okay and but that but that's
that person yeah yeah if I've made the
amends and not person chooses to hold on
to it that just we're yeah but there are
some egregious thing I'm not gonna
forgive you for hurting my child and at
the same time then you've come and
stirred that up again and then like
right well there is part so that's in
the 12 steps that step 9 and we make we
made amends wherever possible except
when to when to do so would injure them
or others and there's like there's a
question like one of the ones that can
come up is like somebody broke the law
and they're wanting to make amends but
if they now but if they now bring it up
like it could devastate their entire
family you know they they they have now
like you know built a family and
everything else but and and if they you
know go and say okay I broke this law
and could end up in jail you know you
it's like figuring out what makes sense
yeah and to me also when you had shared
your piece in the beginning with that in
game a that you go to jail and then
you're it's that's theoretically a road
to redemption and then your thoughts
have served your I don't the worthiness
servant yours and since I like you
you've done what you said like you
committed the crime you've served your
sentence that you're redeemed but in a
way that's true no matter what the crime
is in under the law you're redeems but
also it's absolutely not true because
your criminal record follows you for
your entire life and people don't even
necessarily know like you're just not
gonna hire someone with a criminal
record you're not going to necessarily
get there they're yes here's why I was
there I was in an addiction I was you
know this this big long story and so
therefore having committed a crime once
means that it there is no road to
redemption right it's always gonna be a
mark on your record
no one's gonna hire you which makes it
harder to stay out of crime and harder
to like actually follow the path to
redemption and that's game a but like
how do we deal with that within game B
if like you have actually served your
time if we still have a criminal justice
system in that the same way and how do
we make sure there's space for everyone
because there is a certain amount of
we're killing you by you having a
criminal record right like we'd like go
out and get a job you can't even ever be
on benefits again in this day in the
States when you have a criminal record
but you also can't get a job like it's
it's really difficult you know sorry for
this this we need three different words
he wrote there's three clearly different
domains within this notion of redemption
and they're and they are as far as I can
tell largely separate things right and
so in the nothing that in the example
you've given of a crime being committed
you serve your sentence and you are
redeemed in the eyes of the law but and
exactly as DubLi pointed out by the
letter of the law by the system you are
redeemed by the society you are not
right you you you have not achieved
Redemption and whether you've achieved
redemption inside yourself whether
you've forgiven yourself for the crime
come to terms with whatever that's
that's a third and separate thing right
and you know it may be easier to come to
terms with it you ruin yourself
if those around you have forgiven you
for it you've been accepted back into
the tribe or the society and so on but
they are three largely separate things
I'm not actually sure that Redemption is
the right word for serving a sentence in
a prison unless of course your record is
expunged afterwards right and it doesn't
follow you around in any way then then
possibly so but I I'm really sorry to
come back to where we started because
there was one thing in your opening
Keira which stuck with me as well which
I'd like to come back to was the idea
that game a I come here exactly how you
phrase the game a is characterized by
other by needing to follow the morality
imposed on you by other people
whereas game B is more about an
exploration of your own morality right
and then the difficulty comes what
happens with morality z' differing
moralities have to live in the same
space and
so it needs that we're going slightly
off the topic of redemption here but I
but I think this is a really important
thing that this this idea of different
morality living together it depends on
what you mean by different moralities
right I mean and this is a personal
thing but for me if the actor is acting
in good faith
that's it that's it you know what I mean
everything else should be dealing with
from that position it's just a question
of are the actors acting in good faith
as best they can right what does it mean
to act in good faith well that no III
it's it's it's a deliberately vague
thing but we will understand the notion
right we might disagree in the moment
about whether someone is or is not
acting in good faith right but the
notion of what it means to act in good
faith is something we can all agree on
right that the principle is something we
could we can all agree on would do you
see what I mean as opposed to a in any
given moment evaluating whether or not
that's going on that can cause it that
that's a source of disagreement for sure
yeah for me I think of it in terms of
there's this concept called generosity
assuming the best intentions of the
other person you know assuming that the
other person has the best intentions
yeah I mean I get I guess so but I mean
you very I mean if someone doesn't have
the best intentions making that
assumption very quickly makes you into a
punching bag or a fool or whatever you
know so yeah yes but up to a point I I
don't see it as an absolute position yes
up to a point in an in an initial
interaction yeah yeah yeah yeah that I
would extend that you know if if you say
something that's like completely gonna
front to my morality and assuming that
you're not you know making you know you
say something and assume like say you
call me names or something like that and
assuming that there's a
that there's a valid reason for that and
not immediately jumping to the I'm gonna
fight with you because you know yeah
there's like one of the reasons this
question came up was in the game be
space I interacted with somebody who had
their reputation follow them and I
honestly don't know and I don't think
it's up to me to judge whether the
reputation is fair or not right whether
they did the thing they said you know
they they admit to doing 70% of it I
don't even know what 100% or 70% is but
it was having my interaction with them
which is recorded but not public and
realiz and how much power I had it that
in that interaction that I wasn't really
until the conversation didn't really own
that I could record it then I could edit
it that I can do things with it and and
make him look bad but also like there's
just there are people who are sociopaths
and I just looked up with the actual
proper proper name for the newer name
which is antisocial personality disorder
who are actually really good at
mimicking not being right they can read
the people they can do it and then
there's people who are what I'm gonna
label autistic like myself who come off
like people associate not me necessarily
but associate people who have that under
that umbrella as being antisocial
without the intense being there right
like without office where it's like no I
don't understand the rules if I haven't
stood the runway but I don't understand
them versus I know the rules and I'm
choosing to break them in my own benefit
and as a human you can't necessarily
tell the difference that's an individual
sorry yeah but there's a certain amount
that it doesn't matter in certain
interactions where it's like if I assume
you have a good intent that's gonna do
me better but also I understand that
underlining that you could have bad
intent and as long as I am like if I
hold you to but wait
prove to me you don't have bad intention
that I'm gonna pay that price just like
with the amends and the person holding
on to it right like I'm in it you'd like
you to prove to me you're a good person
you can't you can know someone for 10
years and they could they can do
something that
right and so there's a certain amount of
like owning that like finding I don't
know like and then right before after I
already put out this this question and
decided it to be the question one of
these YouTube videos that I watch he's
this amazing man his name's Chris it's
called special books for special kids
and he interviews different people with
different disabilities a lot of them
from birth whether they're children or
adults and like what is it like to be
you and he's just like this amazing
beautiful man whoo-hoo-hoo you can tell
loves everyone and his one this week was
somebody with with that with a sociopath
who identifies as a sociopath and it's I
haven't even watched the whole interview
yet but it's fascinating because it is
he's he's like I've had to limit my
interaction with people and like Chris
is like yes I didn't know if I could
trust you to have it to have this
interaction and it's fascinating and I
want it I wanted to watch it before
coming on this call but I forgot to
finish watching it and it's like what do
we do with people who have intense like
how can we own that those people exist
have a place in societies we don't want
them all to die and at the same time
realize that when we start categorizing
people like that it's often not the
sociopaths to get categorized because
they're really good at faking it unless
they're honest about that they're fit
you don't even baking it like this is
the interview like how do we not make
our story about someone stamp all the
people who aren't as one and not be able
to register anyone and it's like well
how much does it matter if I'm not
giving you money and I'm not and I'm not
marrying you it doesn't matter if your
intent is good or not you get to own
that I get to own that my intent is good
and I and that no one can know that
right you don't know if you've been like
with what I'm saying is the truth even
though I tried my best to make sure
everything I say is the truth - like TMI
yeah
the so I'm listening
I've I paused listening to John for
Vicky's series for a while and then I
just started listening to it again and
there is
the and and and there's something he
talks about the about cultural grammar
and how that influences our thinking and
the you might my sense is that though
you know those those personality
disorders they're you know there's
several of them then arson you know
narcissistic personality disorder and
antisocial personality disorder
you know they exist or like my senses
they exist for a reason you know they
evolved for a reason and so
understanding what is the value that
they provide in you know in a social
structure and as an as an engineer like
one of the things that I often think
about is you do load testing on a system
you you you do stress testing in order
to figure out where are the weak points
in in a systems and maybe those the
people with those personality disorders
are the ones that are you know nature's
way of creating stress testing for a
society and okay they have value and you
know I mean there's and there being you
know a is there does there does it make
sense in game be to have a prison type
system you know does that does that make
sense that the image that's coming to
mind for me is one of the a li there's a
one of the alien movies where there's a
prison world and they send all of the
you know worst criminals this the you
know planet where they all have to you
know it's it and eventually the prison
closes down but a bunch of them decide
to stay there and you know in
a-and a game being scenario you know are
there certain people that you have to
isolate you know from it from everyone
else because they you know yeah and how
much of it is self isolation versus like
they choose to be there because they're
like right and I'm a danger to society I
don't you know I don't want to be around
people I could harm and how much or the
sign I definitely don't and I definitely
would be game II which is like oh you
have the sociopathic gene you get to go
to this island and like no you haven't
proven yourself you haven't your enemy
and you might be perfectly fine and your
actions might not be just because you
have that yeah and how do you yeah how
do you determine whether or not somebody
is well you know I mean one of the
common things with is someone who is on
one of those personality spectrum
disorders they tend to eventually get
found out and kicked out of a group and
it's and when you have gone to every
group and you can't and and you can't
figure out how to work within you know
within any group then eventually you
find yourself on the outs and that's
actually you know twelve steps and
pacifically like a a and na they are in
many ways people's last stop it is where
you go when you know for a lot of people
that when you you hit rock bottom and
they're it's the one group that will
accept you and I think in a lot of ways
there are there are a lot of people who
end up in those groups who have are on
the spectrum of those disorders and not
now that's just my personal theory I
don't know and they end up you know
no they've they've gone through every
other group to the point of you know
okay I don't have anywhere else to go
the only place that will that will
accept me as this group and the only way
that I can be part of this group not the
only way but the way that I the what
they're suggesting so that I don't like
leave don't go down a path of you know
death by drugs or alcohol is this past
the redemption and so it's a yeah I
don't know if that's hey that feels a
little vulnerable to say because that's
you know it is one of those things of
you know if you they're different
reading you know there are different
reasons I won't say that that's
exclusively why people end up there but
no I think that is like start going no
no no I was just saying that sounds
entirely reasonable there's going to be
lots of people with societal challenges
let's put it that way of one kind or
another right and they get kicked out of
group after group after group and as you
say this is yeah one place that they
know they will be accepted well I do and
so and so just one very final thought
that and that their tendency towards
addiction of one sort or another is
likely to be greater because of that
sense of alienation right and do they
high don't know so I'm not one of those
like do they have a sense of alienation
part of it is they don't they have a
self preserver they like themselves
right at the narcissism but they don't
necessarily have that need for
connection or maybe they I don't
actually know because I'm not know like
because it's no use right they need they
do need an audience yeah they're in
office or sociopath you need an audience
where you need people to manipulate play
with and that is so those people being
in a group together and this is kind of
what I suggest is person I had a
conversation with it's like well if
you're not welcome at my table I need to
make sure there's a table for you but
the table is gonna be filled with people
like you and it's like yeah that sounds
like a horrific place to be and part of
the issue is that like must stamping
people versus that like a bunch of
narcissists together that's gonna be all
of their worst nightmare but like fun
you like figure that out figure out who
that is a bunch of autistic people
together I live in that like I online
and it's beautiful because we got like
we call each other out in ways that are
like
that's not okay no that's not that's not
you don't get to put that under this
umbrella you don't get to like yeah I
get that you don't understand those
rules but that's going too far that's
stalking that's doing it and it actually
works out really well and also not
because autistic people all generally
have two sides of every person is
completely different and it generally is
two extremes it's like your sensory
seeking or your sensory avoidance so
what works for one person wouldn't work
for another
but because we're aware of that there's
something about being able to work
together that works that like is like we
can own that it doesn't work so it works
whereas I don't think that's the way
necessarily with narcissus because they
need the audience they need the people
to manipulate and they're the worst at
manipulating each other they can't write
because they're all everyone's like me
everyone's in are everyone's out to get
their best interests so I'm out to get
my best interest and there isn't people
to like play it with which to me is like
go play your own game figure that out
well and I think there's so going back
to John for Vicki in the last episode
that I watched of him he talked about
the right now he's at the place where
it's he's talking about Martin Luther
and the schism of Protestantism from
Catholicism and the and also the start
of the Scientific Revolution and those
things those two things together
specifically create a situation of
narcissistic cultures that like the
thought process that they or the the the
grammar that came out of their thinking
creates a situation um I
he said he talks about a narcissistic
culture I don't know if he means like
all the individuals within the culture
are narcissistic or the the culture
itself being narcissistic but you know
addressing the you know I need to dig
into that more and understand more but
you know if
the tendency towards narcissism is a
side a side effect of the cultural the
the cultural grammar that we have been
born into then there's different
extremes and so you know in a lot of
cases people who end up in like AAA or
NA there there's there's several
different 12-step groups but there's
something called ACA which is adult
children of alcoholics and dysfunctional
families and that's for because once we
get sober you kind of realize oh wait a
minute that didn't actually fixed a lot
of the shame that I feel that's
underneath that comes from you know the
fact that I grew up in a dysfunctional
family where the goalposts was
constantly being moved and I wa and
shame was the main tool used to get me
to behave and so it it's it's very and
if you grew up with a narcissistic
parent the likelihood that you're going
to be a narcissist is very high but
there is also a path out of that if one
so it's this you know I would I I have
I'm okay with acknowledging that I am
that I am on that narcissistic spectrum
I mean I think everyone I think everyone
exists on the narcissistic spectrum but
I'm further over on that side just
because of the environment that I grew
up in and and so I have to do a lot of
work in order to heal all of the
that I got and in order to you know and
and so like I have a lot of different
tools that help me on that path to
redemption so I don't know if that again
it's
what makes that space well if I can just
slightly put it into a different frame
exactly what you were saying but just in
a slightly different framework and that
the idea of niche creation right and so
in the culture in which we exist there
are advantages to exploiting the niche
of being a narcissist right you can get
the sense of validation you know what I
mean you can get the attention of others
this kind of thing by behaving in a
statistic way similar similarly
sociopathy there's a there is a niche in
existence in the culture to make it
worthwhile to exploit that niche if you
can manipulate other people to do your
bidding well that's less stuff that you
have to do for yourself right and so it
these are I I personally don't see these
things to a large degree as
physiological type psychological issues
right they are there in my view they are
entirely inculcated and so my point the
point I'm trying to make is that the
notion of separating out the sociopaths
on the narcissists from the game be were
because they're going to up the
game be dynamics I think is I think as a
profoundly flawed view a I have a
inherent aversion to be any situation in
which one group of people gets to point
of another group of people and say we
don't like that and we want you
separated from us I mean whatever it is
I have an aversion I have a deep deep
deep seated aversion to that and that
power always like I said great
say any identify any any other segment
of the population as being unworthy or
undesirable or whatever for any reason
however well-intentioned because sooner
or later that becomes a much much bigger
thing and more and more groups start to
get singled out as being do you know
what I mean the hole that it's a path
you simply can't begin to go down
however well-intentioned the first step
on that path might be it's a path that
simply needs to remain blocked off in my
opinion and I think as a group you can
say you are or aren't welcome in this
group which is different than we're
better than you because we have this
care
drastic just you're not and I'm wonder
is with all those the same thing to you
and like girl group to be able to make
metrics as to who's included and who's
not included global societies the level
I was talking on so when we come if
you're coming down to the sort of level
of a Facebook group kind of thing then
yeah I mean I get yeah yeah I'm really
really really in two minds about this
we're not on the one hand obviously the
administration of the group have the
right to kick anyone out but any or no
reason in the same way that the you know
the proprietor of a public establishment
has the reason it has the right to kick
people out for any or no reason if they
don't want them in there you know what I
mean it's it's it's your right to do
that it's it's it's your thing it's your
right to do that however given the
nature of what game B is I really do
think that if we can't figure out
solutions to the little spats that we
have among a group of people who are all
fundamentally on the same team right
otherwise it wouldn't be here then what
hope is there of ever rolling it out on
a sort of global kind of scale so I
really do think more effort could be put
into resolving these things whatever
they are because yeah for exactly that
reason I just it just sets a bad tone
you know if sorry gone done know what I
was gonna say is you know I mean one of
the pieces is I think part of what's
gonna what is gonna come out or what I
see coming out of game B or at least my
or let me backtrack the thing that has
come out as a result of my transition
into game beeping and a desire to a deep
desire to see the best in everyone and
to or not is to not assume the best be
aware of boundaries and also recognize
that you know the thing a lot of the
things especially with no narcissism
narcissism in particular more so than
sociopathy is
is healed through community it is healed
through being accepted for who you are
and you know again psychopathy and
sociopathy I don't know as much about
and I don't know you know to what extent
it's you know it's it's inheritable
versus nature versus nurture but you
know that that process of you know can't
we love you and there's a I listen to a
lot of Tara brach and I'm reminded of a
story that she talks about about again
about a tribe where they if some woman
gets if someone in the tribe gets sick
they all come together and they and
everyone tells all of the things they've
been keeping that they've been keeping
to themselves like it's it's a community
like in order to heal an individual you
have to the whole community has to
participate in that healing process and
so when we kick someone out of a you
know of a group it we're saying okay
you're not you know you don't fit into
this group and to what extent is that
person manifesting all of the shadow of
everyone else within that community
that's a good question how did that and
and and an individual's path to
redemption is part of the communal path
to redemption mm-hmm and so you know
it's this you know it is that how do you
find the balance between individual and
the community and there being a you know
and
disconnection we have to how we are all
connected as a community which I mean
one of the qualities of being a
narcissist
especially as a parent is that you have
like a scapegoat and a golden child
right that you kind of pass those things
onto and that's literally what the
community does is like well let's make
this person a scapegoat and kick them
out and with them go all our problems
right right and we turn people into
golden child but like they get to be the
and it's in our individual lives we i we
are reflected the shadow and light of
everyone that we encounter and so when
someone annoys us it's because it's our
shadow when someone's like when we hold
someone to high esteem it's generally a
light it's not always the case but I
never I come from that spin there's
always something for me to learn and
it's not kicking the person out because
it's like right there's shadow for us to
learn if we didn't have any of this
shadow it wouldn't matter how they
showed up and so like owning a little
bit of that it was just like what came
up for you were talking it was like oh
we're turning them into the shadow and
they are the scapegoat and kicking them
out and like good now we don't have to
deal with that anymore gone no it's
gonna show up again and again and again
there was something about the tone as
well which which is troubling me I'm a
couple of those posts as well as there's
there's there's an intolerance in the
tone nothing specific in the language
but there's just something and listen
that could be me projecting into it is
the thing with tone in writing right
you're never quite sure what the
intended tone of the writer was but I
detect I detect a somewhat hostile and
intolerant tone sometimes you know one
other thing I made a comment on one of
the threads that I think that what we're
gonna what we're eventually going to see
is that there is groups are going to
emerge around a ratio of
conflict to conflict resolution like a
group a group is only going to be able
to maintain coherence if or no
very friction to a ratio of friction to
brain fart um what's the word I'm
thinking of conflict resolution there we
go no because you have to have in order
for a group to like make forward motion
you have to have friction but if you
have too much friction and not enough
conflict resolution then the group's
breakup and so you know trusting that
you know okay right now maybe it would
be nicer you know it would be better to
be able to handle and look at the shadow
that this Perez look at more of the
shadow that this person is bringing up
but maybe there's not enough great
conflict resolution to do with it
there's not enough skill within the
group to be a conflict resolution to be
able to do that and that's not a it's
not a judgement but it would be a this
is you know Erik going back to what you
said earlier about this is a something
to aim that that we want to increase our
ability our our conflict resolution
skills in order to be able to handle
more friction in order to make more
progress in whatever direction we're
trying to go in between like the
Facebook group which we all know is not
game B versus game B in the future
whenever you know which is like we're
all living it's different game B visions
anyway but having it was I my point of
that Oh like when I look at the criminal
justice system in game a and the reason
people ends up there and I can see much
more compassionate ways to deal with all
of those conflicts then what we
currently do right with domestic
violence like there is a way to keep a
family together or keep sovereignty over
people while keeping people safe that we
don't do ready you know we make we make
it very like it's all on him and also
like he's done wrong and he can't be
redeemed and she needs to be kept safe
and it's like okay there's truce little
tiny bit
truth there but the vast majority is
like you're both wounded individuals you
both have fault and how do we how do you
think you and how do you think we keep
you safe
right like having the people who are in
the conflict or having come out of the
conflict that exact conflict what does
what does it look like right having kids
who are taken out of their homes and put
into foster care asks how could we have
kept your family together when there are
adults that have it you know more
perspective on it how would that have
worked how could we have kept you with
your family with the addiction with the
poverty and had that work had it you
know like or were you happy to be taken
out right and there's gonna be differing
opinions there's gonna be so how do we
distinguish between kids that should be
removed in kids they should stay how do
we not ignore the problem but deal with
it and I it's a higher level of conflict
resolution like being present with the
dysfunction treating it as it is instead
of criminalizing it and making it be
something that has to stop now when it's
like it's it's playing itself out
there's a there's a reason it's here and
you're not getting to the root cause of
it you're not getting to not passing
that trauma on to another generation
like well like well violence is
happening so we're gonna commit this
other violence to stop that violence
because taking a kid away from their
family is always violent it's just is it
the lesser of the two and they don't
honor it like that it's like no we gotta
take em all over the state we know
what's best right well and there's the
what comes up for me is like people how
much are people identified with the
victim consciousness and but not only
victim consciousness but also the hero
consciousness like we have to protect
you know it's our job to protect people
and what and the rush that people get
from that like well I I'm a good person
because I'm rescuing people and how much
is rescues victims right Yeah right
exactly yeah yeah yeah it's a really
really really interesting dynamic I
think it might have been you that
there's a triangle or something and some
equipment is really really interesting I
know that it's a it's a lens that stuck
with me it's really it strikes me that a
really simple change of name would have
a profound effect if you change the
criminal justice system into the
conflict resolution service yeah I mean
it's just boom you know what I mean
straight away just just with the change
of name if you did nothing else
different just the change of name would
alter the expectations of everyone
involved in it and everyone going into
it I feel like no it would not because
only because we do like the government
does those things all the time therefore
they caught they call something by a
different name it's like the family
together in this project run away from
like it's like it's not just change but
if we were going to look at revamping it
with that being the title what could we
do that's not tearing it down to zero
there's a reason we it exists we want to
keep people say if we want to you know
not have constant murder and stealing
and all these things there's also my
brain is blanking on the name of it but
there's a I'll have to look it up it's a
way of creative it's a combination of
conflict resolution and like social
justice but it's ya know I'm gonna have
to look it up and tell you guys later
but it's it's essentially a how do you
bring together how do you how do you a
well use a wrong has been committed and
how do you bring resolution through the
whole community in terms of the victim
being heard the the the perpetrator you
know
making amends you know but it's done
within the community one of the things
we have that we already have there I
mean it's been perverted and with
but we already have that common law is
exactly is exactly there I mean that's
that's the whole notion of common law
right you got the aggrieved and the
agree ver together you have a mediating
group of people there that allow both
sides of the arguments be put the truth
to be reached and then appropriate
reparations to be to be made you know I
mean that's exactly what common law is
all about at its core is not that
anymore but that's that's the notion and
the one that I'm thinking about is more
in terms of like a situation with you
know common law is you're dealing with
you know more of the crimes whereas this
dispute any dispute over anything at all
yeah so we only have two minutes left to
wrap this up and then I had a question
because if I start it now it's gonna
spark a whole thing and then but um and
then we can stop going live and do
figure out the question for next week
okay I think I'm gonna see you both in
an hour and a half it or next thing
that's what you do but they don't have
any closing thoughts comments
listen I've enjoyed this conversation
there's I mean there's a lot that's like
being passed around and things were
trying to sort out yeah I also this is a
difficult conversation or the
conversation was enjoyable but the topic
is like there's a lot here the person to
tackle this for weeks on weeks yeah well
and there is also the sense of it's all
theoretical there's nothing like there's
no concrete action to take and that can
be enough difficult at times yes
absolutely
Eric you've anything you want to say
well just just just as I said earlier on
I think I think I've sort of thought
about in the intervening time and I
think three different words are needed
so for me and this is just my own
personal view redemption is the inner
thing right of forgiving yourself
whatever making yourself better
forgiveness is that which is bestowed
upon you by the outside world and then
repaying your debt is the very much
lower third brother
if you
which is there which is the fulfilling
the requirements of the system for the
wrong that you've done okay
thanks again if I send it all right
goodbye YouTube